Syed Younus Ali

London, UK

Mobile: 07949972554 Email: syounusa@yahoo.com

Portfolio: syedmyali.github.io, GitHub Id: syedmyali, LinkedIn Id: syedmyali

NOTE: British Citizen (No work visa or sponsorship required)

Personal Profile

I am an Engineering Professional with several years' experience in the energy and aerospace industry, where I have worked for different companies in engineering, analysis and design role. All of my skills set are in core technical areas and liaise with suppliers, clients and vendors which will be helpful transferable skills in the software development industry.

I'm a fast learner with engineering, design and development mind-set which will be my strengths to excel the potentials in the software development environment.

I'm passionate to be a dedicated software developer through-out my rest of the career.

IT Skills

Software Development (Front End): HTML, CSS, JavaScript, Typescript, Bootstrap, React, Angular Software Development (Back End): Java, Python, SQL (MySQL, Oracle), NOSQL (Mongo DB) Technology/Frameworks: Maven, Spring Boot, Rest API, Micro services, MVC, JDBC, JUnit, Postman Cloud/ Version Control: AWS (S3, EC2, Elastic Beanstalk, ECS..), Azure, Docker, Git, Git Hub

Education and IT Training

01/2022-03/2022	Just IT Training Ltd, London
	Digital Skills Bootcamp: Software Development
	A twelve week intensive bootcamp covering the fundamentals of full
	stack Software development.
10/2021-01/2022	City Lit, London
	Boot Camp: Java Programming
	A twelve week intensive boot camp covering the fundamentals of
	Java programming language.
06/2021-09/2021	City Lit, London
	Boot camp: Python Programming
	A four month intensive boot camp covering the python
	programming language and final project.
09/2008-10/2009	University of Portsmouth, Portsmouth, UK
09/2008-10/2009	University of Portsmouth, Portsmouth, UK MSc in Mechanical and Manufacturing Engineering
09/2008-10/2009 Core Modules:	•
	MSc in Mechanical and Manufacturing Engineering
	MSc in Mechanical and Manufacturing Engineering Reverse Engineering, Stress Analysis, Computational Fluid Dynamics,
Core Modules:	MSc in Mechanical and Manufacturing Engineering Reverse Engineering, Stress Analysis, Computational Fluid Dynamics, Energy Management, Composite Materials, Project Management
Core Modules:	MSc in Mechanical and Manufacturing Engineering Reverse Engineering, Stress Analysis, Computational Fluid Dynamics, Energy Management, Composite Materials, Project Management 'Fatigue strength analysis of high chromium alloyed steel specimen'
Core Modules: Final Year Project:	MSc in Mechanical and Manufacturing Engineering Reverse Engineering, Stress Analysis, Computational Fluid Dynamics, Energy Management, Composite Materials, Project Management 'Fatigue strength analysis of high chromium alloyed steel specimen' supervised by SIEMENS (VAI) and University of Portsmouth.
Core Modules: Final Year Project:	MSc in Mechanical and Manufacturing Engineering Reverse Engineering, Stress Analysis, Computational Fluid Dynamics, Energy Management, Composite Materials, Project Management 'Fatigue strength analysis of high chromium alloyed steel specimen' supervised by SIEMENS (VAI) and University of Portsmouth. Bangladesh University of Engineering and Technology, Bangladesh
Core Modules: Final Year Project: 08/1997-05/2004	MSc in Mechanical and Manufacturing Engineering Reverse Engineering, Stress Analysis, Computational Fluid Dynamics, Energy Management, Composite Materials, Project Management 'Fatigue strength analysis of high chromium alloyed steel specimen' supervised by SIEMENS (VAI) and University of Portsmouth. Bangladesh University of Engineering and Technology, Bangladesh BSc in Mechanical Engineering
Core Modules: Final Year Project: 08/1997-05/2004	MSc in Mechanical and Manufacturing Engineering Reverse Engineering, Stress Analysis, Computational Fluid Dynamics, Energy Management, Composite Materials, Project Management 'Fatigue strength analysis of high chromium alloyed steel specimen' supervised by SIEMENS (VAI) and University of Portsmouth. Bangladesh University of Engineering and Technology, Bangladesh BSc in Mechanical Engineering Computer Programming Language, Numerical Analysis, Fluid
Core Modules: Final Year Project: 08/1997-05/2004	MSc in Mechanical and Manufacturing Engineering Reverse Engineering, Stress Analysis, Computational Fluid Dynamics, Energy Management, Composite Materials, Project Management 'Fatigue strength analysis of high chromium alloyed steel specimen' supervised by SIEMENS (VAI) and University of Portsmouth. Bangladesh University of Engineering and Technology, Bangladesh BSc in Mechanical Engineering Computer Programming Language, Numerical Analysis, Fluid Mechanics, Production Processes, Machine Design, Control
Core Modules: Final Year Project: 08/1997-05/2004 Core Modules:	MSc in Mechanical and Manufacturing Engineering Reverse Engineering, Stress Analysis, Computational Fluid Dynamics, Energy Management, Composite Materials, Project Management 'Fatigue strength analysis of high chromium alloyed steel specimen' supervised by SIEMENS (VAI) and University of Portsmouth. Bangladesh University of Engineering and Technology, Bangladesh BSc in Mechanical Engineering Computer Programming Language, Numerical Analysis, Fluid Mechanics, Production Processes, Machine Design, Control Engineering, Industrial Management, Renewable Energy

Projects:

File Management Utility App: The application stores excel files and have view edit and delete functionalities for each file. It has service access authorization and user authentication capabilities.

Programming language and frameworks used: Java, Spring-boot, Angular, MySQL. Application deployed on AWS.

University Alumni Tracking Application: The project is a database oriented GUI application which stores the alumni information inputted by individual alumni. Ultimate goal of this app is to track the individual alumni's updated information.

Medicine Expiry Checker App: The idea behind this project was to save the public health and money. Every year only in UK alone, tens of millions pounds worth of medicine is wasted just because of proper expiry checking systems are not deployed in the medicine stores and pharmacies. This App would be beneficial as it displays the medication expiry time line along with the stock status.

Film Flix App: This is a CURD application which stores the film details and user can add film details and show them accordingly, any existing items can be updated and deleted from the list as well.

Employment History

03/2022-Present

INFOSYS Limited, Canary Wharf London Software Development Associate

- Working in a full stack development and operations team in the enterprise applications.
- Main language, Java along with Spring Boot framework and associated modern technologies.
- SQL/NOSQL database and cloud system (AWS, Azure, GCP).

01/2021-05/2021 03/2019-08/2019

Caley Ocean systems Ltd, Glasgow

Senior Mechanical Design Engineer (Contract)

- Carried out Stress/strain/vibration/fatigue and over all structural integrity analysis of mechanical/hydraulic systems in aid of ANSYS, Solid Works, Mathcad and hand calculations.
- Produced 3D prototypes and 2D drawings to relevant standards and best practices

09/2019-12/2020

Lagoni Engineering, London Senior Design Engineer (Contract)

- Structural analysis of piping, mechanical and hydraulic systems against industry standards, codes and best practices; validated through hand calculations and market leading analysis tools/software.
- Produced, checked and approved engineering documentation (piping material specifications, Pipe supports, data sheet, manual, SOP, FAT, Design Review)

10/2017-02/2019

National Oilwell Varco, Glasgow Senior Design Engineer (Contract)

- Generated compliance matrix, data sheet, product specification, Basis of Design (BoD) standard operating procedure (SOP), test plan/procedure.
- Involved in Finite Element Analysis (FEA) and hand calculation to validate the final physical product using industry standard simulation packages.

06/2012-09/2017

Aquaterra Energy Limited, Norwich Mechanical Design Engineer

- Designed prototypes of Topsides, Well Head Support Structure (WSS), Centralisers, Running Tools,
 Drilling Templates, Tension Ring, Riser Monitoring System (RMS), Lifting System, Test Jigs etc.
- Prepared Factory Acceptance Test report, In house testing, Installation procedure, and Front End Engineering Design report, manufacturing drawings, Bill of Materials, Schematics and Layout.

11/2009-05/2012

GBM Minerals Engineering Limited, London Mechanical Design Engineer

- Participated in client design review for project deliverables and prepared specifications
- Designed mechanical and piping components in AutoCAD Plant 3D.

04/2005-05/2007

Bashundhara Paper Mills Ltd, Bangladesh Assistant Mechanical Engineer

References available upon request